Guide to the James Emmet Brenner Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
James Emmet Brenner papers
1932-1951
SC0053
Brenner, James Emmet, 1890-1963.
2 Linear feet
Correspondence, reports, committee minutes, memoranda, surveys and other miscellaneous materials relating to the Stanford Law School, primarily between 1946 and 1951. Correspondents include Jim Ellis, David S. Jacobson, Francis V. Keesling, Carl Spaeth, Arthur T. Vanderbilt and Earl Warren.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, Law School, 1966.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of law at Stanford (1927-1955; emeritus 1955-1963).
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, reports, committee minutes, memoranda, surveys and other miscellaneous materials relating to the Stanford Law School, primarily between 1946 and 1951. Correspondents include Jim Ellis, David S. Jacobson, Francis V. Keesling, Carl Spaeth, Arthur T. Vanderbilt and Earl Warren.
Access Terms
Brenner, James Emmet, 1890-1963.; Ellis, Jim.; Jacobson, David S.; Keesling, Francis V.; Spaeth, Carl B.; Stanford University. School of Law--Faculty.; Vanderbilt, Arthur T., 1888-1957.; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974.; Minutes.; Surveys.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Ellis, Jim - correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ellis to Brenner, TLS re Republican Strategy Committee, 1951 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Brenner to Ellis, TL re Republican Grass Roots Platform, 1951 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Republican Plan, presented to the Republican National Committee in Chicago, Illinois, 1949 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Holleck, Charles A., Congressman, Illinois. Includes speech given by Holleck, "The Role of the Lawyer in Government.", 1950 December 11 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with David S. Jacobson. Includes materials on fund drive for Law School Plan, Annual Appeal Committee for the Stanford fund (list), Law School business, recommendations for law school students, Law Society "list". Brenner as Secretary of the Law School Plan., 1946 May 9 - 1951 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Keesling, Francis V., Chairman, Law School Plan - correspondence with, 1948 June 12 - 1951 November 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Address by Francis V. Keesling delivered at 50th reunion - class of '98, 1948 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Law School Fund circular letters, Stanford Law School Plan (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - List of names of law school graduates since 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Current activities of Keesling and Keesling (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Proposal for more extensive Scholarship funds (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Spaeth, Carl, Dean of Law School - correspondence with, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Law School Plan, Law School administrative business, requests for letters of appreciation, proposal for a third-year seminar and legal writing project. (Box 1, 5)
    - Faculty biography of Deal Carl B. Spaeth and other members of the Law School (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Circulars re Law School Plan. Inventory of law school books received from Judge Curtis Wilbur, Robert Z. Hawkins, Charles A. Cantwell (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Establishment of title "Lecturer in Law", Stanford Law Review (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Library acquisitions, Spaeth - Report to Law Alumni; Crothers Hall Library; Law School student placement (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Preliminary report on shelving of Law Library in new Law School quarters (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Vanderbelt, Arthur T. - correspondence with, 1947 September 20 - 1949 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Survey of legal profession, American Bar Association (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Circulars for survey of legal profession (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Copy of questions used in the survey of legal profession (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annual survey of American law, Bar examinations (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Warren, Earl, Governor of California - correspondence with, 1949 April 5 - 1951 August 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Brenner retiring from Board of Governors of Maritime Academy (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Campaign contributions (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Stanford Law School Plan - miscellaneous materials, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Includes information related to Law School Plan contributors, officers, and Stanford Law Society (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Law Library materials, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Law Library Committee, notes of meetings, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Statistics for library for the years 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Swiss Bar Association - correspondence with, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Law Library expenditures, library control problems with suggested solutions, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Gifts sent for the Faculty Library and Conference Room, books to be purchased by Judge Crother for the library in Crother Hall, selected editions for the law library (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Law Society - includes circular letters and memorandum to Placement Committee (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Crothers Hall, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Judge Crothers - correspondence with. Includes correspondence between Judge Crothers to Dean Spaeth, and puchase of books for Crothers Hall Law Library., 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence between Judge Crothers and Lennihan, David W., Librarian of Crothers Hall Law Library, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Photocopies of Crothers Hall floor plan (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Revised budget for Crothers Hall Law Library, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mailing list for Crothers Book - additional names; suggested textbook purchases for Crothers Hall Law Library
  - Stanford Law School Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Stanford Law Review (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Executive Committee of the Stanford Law Society of Northern California, Stanford Law Review subscriptions (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - List of people given copies of Law Review; legal writing report 1948-1949; President's Report for Volume 1 of the Stanford Law Review; President's Report for Volume 2 of the Stanford Law Review (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - On the Job Training (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - List of who to send letters to re summer office work for G.I. law students; letters of reply from law firms in the bay area. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Internship program - Summer, 1948 List of students placed with various law firms in Bay Area and California (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence with following cooperating law firms: Rogers and Clark, San Francisco Stafford and Crist, Palo Alto Frank V. Campbell, San Jose Irvin H. Frasse, San Jose M. Burr Wellington, Santa Ana Forrest Betts, Los Angeles (not G. I. Intern Program) Bert W. Levitt, San Francisco Robert Littler, San Francisco Duncan Oneal, San Jose Fred Wool, San Jose Arthur B. Dunne, San Francisco Seth Millington, Gridley Harlow Rothert, San Francisco Frank B. Belcher, Los Angeles Frank Coakley, Oakland James C. Ingebretsen, Los Angeles George W. Dryer, Los Angeles Beresford and Adams, San Jose Fogel and McInerny, Santa Monica Judge Hardy, Palo Alto, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Internship program - Summer 1949 List of students placed with various law firms in Bay Area and California (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with the following cooperating law firms: Beresford and Adams, San Jose Adams, Sugue, Davis and Hazeltine, Los Angeles Robert N. Baker, Santa Monica Charles E. Beardsley, Los Angeles Dickson, Ellis, Parsons and McCrea, Salt Lake City Frank B. Belcher, Los Angeles J. F. Coakley, Oakland Frank L. Crist, Palo Alto Eustace Cullinan, San Francisco James L. Sairs, Santa Ana George W. Dryer, Los Angeles Jesse Feldman, San Francisco Fogel and McInerny Gibson, Dunn and Crutcher, Los Angeles Fred D. Johnston, Santa Ana Cuthrie, Longan and Jordan, San Bernadino Landels and Weigel, San Francisco Bert W. Levit, San Francisco Kenneth R. McDougall, Palo Alto James E. Mack, South Palo Alto Ray, Quinney and Nebeker, Salt Lake City Lynn S. Richards, Salt Lake City Hancock, Rothert and Low, San Francisco Rogers P. Smith, San Francisco James E. Walker, Santa Ana Wilson and Wilson, San Bernardino Fred A. Wool, San Jose J. E. Simpson, Los Angeles, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Internship - General, 1948 March 13 - 1950 May 27 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous form letters to cooperating law firms setting up a course in "law internship", 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Form letters to law students (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Internship requests from students (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Law 288, supervised law office study, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous materials related to the Stanford Law School (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - General rules for practice court (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Articles of Association and By-Laws of Association of California Law Schools (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Notes for "Contract for Sale of Farm Lands", 1935 January 9 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Loan fund of Stanford University Libraries, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence; Delta Theta Phi; law books (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Samples: agreement of trust, last will and testament, declaration of trust (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Memoradum on the teaching of legal ethics, legal history, etc. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Year books (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Memos to committee on Law Review of the Stanford Law Society (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Practicing Law Series (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - American Association of University Professors, Stanford Chapter - collective decreasing life insurance for the Stanford faculty, 1950 February 10 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Lower Division Administration, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Preliminary report of the Committee on Lower Division Administration (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Report of the Committee to the Academic Council, 1950 May 16 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Illustrative Citations I, claims in actions against government agencies and officials (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Teaching Fellows on Legal Writing, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Report of the Committee on Seminars, Law School; including draft report of 1949, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Forms of gifts, grants, devises and bequests, general and special conditional and unconditional to the Board of Trustees, 1938 January 6 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and circulars; memoranda to Deans; Academic Council election results (May 1951); Stanford faculty speaker service (October 1950); articles of incorporation; by-laws, share certificate of a California corporation (specimin), 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence re the Burton-Ball-Hatch bill in Congress. Correspondents include: James E. Brenner, Herbert W. Clark, Joseph H. Hall, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)